Guide to the Texas Optometric Association Records
University of Houston Libraries
Texas Optometric Association Records
undated
09/2006-001
Texas Optometric Association
6.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains five series: The TOA President Correspondence, Executive Secretary Correspondence, TOA Committee Correspondence, TOA Administration, and Audio Tapes. Material includes correspondence, memoranda, meetings, newspaper clippings, reports, audio tapes and other administrative material.
Historical Note:
Founded in 1900, The Texas Optometric Association (TOA) represents more than 1200 doctors of optometry, optometry students, and optometric technicians across the State of Texas. Originally, the organization was named the Texas Optical Association, later named the Texas Optometric Association. The TOA began organizing local societies in 1943. In 1987, it had 972 members and 21 local societies. TOA offers a variety of services including job referral, continuing education courses, insurance, travel benefits, periodicals, and meeting and conference opportunities. The Texas Optometric Association has been an essential advocate for Texas optometrists and has maintained its headquarters in Austin since 1951.
With the promise of substantial financial assistance from TOA pledges, the University of Houston College of Optometry, became the tenth optometry school in the nation, in 1952. At that time, the university was a private school, but in 1963, it became a state-supported college. Today UHCO is one of only 17 optometry schools in the United States. The institution offers a four-year program of instruction and clinical experience for the Doctor of Optometry degree. It also offers M.S. and Ph.D. degree programs in physiological optics for those who plan careers in research or teaching. By 1987, it had awarded 23 Ph.D. degrees, 34 M.S. degrees, and more than 1,500 O.D. degrees.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Audiotapes; Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence; Publications (document genre)
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains five series: The TOA President Correspondence, Executive Secretary Correspondence, TOA Committee Correspondence, TOA Administration, and Audio Tapes. Material includes correspondence, memoranda, meetings, newspaper clippings, reports, audio tapes and other administrative material. The collection is arranged chronologically within each series, adhering as much as possible to the original order.
Detailed List of Contents
- TOA President, Correspondence, 1954-1989
  - Armistead, B.W., February 1955-August 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armistead, B.W., September 1955-November 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Day, Bob, August 1974-November 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bridwell, Jack, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bridwell, Jack, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fruge, Phillip R., November 1986-April 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kemp, William N., April 1969-February 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kemp, William N., April 1972-August 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lewis, Philip, May 1973-March 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - McCall, John A., July 1987-December 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - McNeil, Jimmy W., June 1974-December 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Peterson, Robert H., June 1987-June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pettey, W.A., April 1950-December 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pettey, W.A., January 1954-December 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pettey, W.A., January 1960-December 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Thornton, Floyd, February 1985-February 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Treadwell, W.C. Jr., March 1977-April 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Armistead, B.W., August 1954-April 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Armistead, B.W., May 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Armistead, B.W., June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
  - Armistead, B.W., July 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Armistead, B.W., August 1955-September 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Armistead, B.W., October 1955-November 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Armistead, B.W., December 1956-January 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Armistead, B.W., February 1957-March 1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Armistead, B.W., April 1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Armistead, B.W., May 1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Armistead, B.W., June 1957-September 1957 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Armistead, B.W., September 1957-January 1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Day, Bob, July 1974-January 1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bridwell, Jack, January 1976-May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bridwell, Jack, June 1976-October 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bridwell, Jack, June 1976-January 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bridwell, Jack, February 1977-August 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fruge, Phillip R., December 1985-April 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Kemp, William N., April 1971-December 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kemp, William N., January 1972-September 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kemp, William N., October 1972-January 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lewis, Philip, March 1973-June 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lewis, Philip, July 1973-September 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lewis, Philip, October 1973-December 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lewis, Philip, January 1974-March 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lewis, Philip, April 1974-May 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lewis, Philip, June 1974-August 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lewis, Philip, September 1974-December 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lewis, Philip, January 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lewis, Philip, February 1975-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - McCall, John A., March 1988-March 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - McNeil, Jimmy W., January 1975-June 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - McNeil, Jimmy W., July 1975-October 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - McNeil, Jimmy W., November 1975-April 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Peterson, Robert H., July 1987-July 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Pettey, W.A., January 1958-December 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Thornton, Floyd L., September 1984-January 1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Threadwell, W.C. Jr., January 1977-May 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Threadwell, W.C. Jr., June 1977-August 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Threadwell, W.C. Jr., September 1977-December 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Threadwell, W.C. Jr., January 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Threadwell, W.C. Jr., February 1978-May 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Executive Secretary, Correspondence, 1965-1990
  - Boysen, Stanley, February 1968-December 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Boysen, Stanley, July 1976-June 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Boysen, Stanley, July 1985-December 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Boysen, Stanley, January 1989-December 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Boysen, Stanley, December 1965-September 197 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Boysen, Stanley, October 1973-March 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Boysen, Stanley, April 1974-October 1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Boysen, Stanley, November 1974-May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Boysen, Stanley, June 1975-February 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Boysen, Stanley, March 1976-July 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Boysen, Stanley, August 1976-May 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Boysen, Stanley, June 1977-September 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Boysen, Stanley, October 1977-December 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Boysen, Stanley, January 1986-December 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Boysen, Stanley, January 1988-June 1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- TOA Committees, Correspondence
  - October 1968-April 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - May 1974-July 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - August 1975-February 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - March 1976-November 1977 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - January 1978-December 1985 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - January-August 1990 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Postcards, 1977-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Texas State Board of Medical Examiners, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Texas Optometry Association Administration
  - Attorney's General's Opinion, June 1934-November 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Benefits - Insurance (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Benefits - Healthcare (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Benefits - Medicaid (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Brochures (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
  - Budgets (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Budgets - Bob Day (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Budgets - Purchasing (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Budgets - Legislative Budget Board (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - By-Laws (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
  - Committees - Conferences and Meetings (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Committees - Guidelines and Duties (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Committees - Member Lists (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Committees - Non-Member Lists (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Committees - Membership (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Committees - Questionnaires (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Committees - Reports (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Committees - Student Affairs (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Committees - Survey (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - Erisa Cases - AOA Bulletins, 1985-1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Erisa Cases - Articles (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Erisa Cases - Supreme Court and U.S. Court of Appeals (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ethnic Grievance Committee, 1972-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ethnic Grievance Committee, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - FTC - Proposed Ophthalmic Practice (Box 5, Folder 6-10)
  - FTC - Eyeglasses II Proposal (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1990 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters - Texas Optometry Board (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Organization Charts (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Publication (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Publication - Articles (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Publication - "Moving Toward the Future" (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Publication - Optometry's Plan for Legislative Action (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Publication - Ophthalmic Practice Rules (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publication - Oral Argument (Box 6, Folder 3-6)
  - Publication - Publishing Agreement (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Publication - The Report of the Pennsylvania OA (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Publication - Southwestern Congress of Optometry (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Publication - Texas Optometry Act 2005 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Publication - Texas State Board of Medical Examiners (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Publication - U.S. Court of Appeals (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Publication - U.S. Federal Trade Commission (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
  - Publication - U.S. Federal Trade Commission Rule (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Publication - Vision Therapy (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Vision USA Workshop (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Audio Tapes
  - House Committee on Public Health, 76th Legislature, March 1999 (Folder 18)